<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gemitus plebis: or A mournful complaint and supplication in behalf of the more weak and ignorant of the people of this nation. Drawn up for them by a friend, whose deep sense of his own ignorance and weakness, hath taught him to be compassionate towards all that labour under the same infirmities. / By C. Raie.</title>
            <author>Raie, C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E886_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203325</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E886[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gemitus plebis: or A mournful complaint and supplication in behalf of the more weak and ignorant of the people of this nation. Drawn up for them by a friend, whose deep sense of his own ignorance and weakness, hath taught him to be compassionate towards all that labour under the same infirmities. / By C. Raie.</title>
                  <author>Raie, C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 23, 32-34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Ibbitson, for Tho. Newberry, at the sign of the Three Lyons in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb: 3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115496:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Gemitus Plebis:</hi> OR A Mournful Complaint AND SUPPLICATION In behalf of the more weak and ignorant of the people of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Drawn up for them by a Friend, whoſe deep ſenſe of his own ignorance and weakneſs, hath taught him to be compaſſionate towards all that labour under the ſame infirmities.</p>
            <p>By <hi>C. RAIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>We roar all like Bears, and mourn ſore like Doves, we look for judgement, but there is none, for ſalvation, but it is far from us,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Tolerabilius eſt Deo quempiam cum ignorantia in humilitate jacere, quam cum elatione alta ſapere, <bibl>
                  <hi>Greg. in Mor.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Si propter eos ſolos Chriſtus mortuus eſt, qui certa intelligentia poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt iſta diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnere, penè fruſtra in eccleſia laboramus, <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt. 102.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Ibbitſan,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Newberry,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Three Lyons</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115496:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable the Knights and Burgeſses, choſen for this preſent Parliament in the County of <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>NOBLE PATRIOTS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Supplication which now preſents it ſelf unto your Honours view, was drawn up in much grief and anguiſh of ſpirit, lamenting to ſee the ſad condition of the people of this Nation, in order to their ſouls, and everlaſting ſtate; whilſt after a long expectation of ſome happy Reformation, they are found partly ſinking by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees into the gulf of Prophaneneſs and Atheiſme, partly hurried on by the wind of ſtrange doctrines upon the rocks of Heretical opinions, deſtructive to the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of our holy Religion: Not much unlike the caſe of that ſhip wherein St. <hi>Paul</hi> was driven to <hi>Malta,</hi> whereof<note place="margin">Act 27. 7</note> one part ſtuck faſt in the earth, the other part was broken and driven away by violent waves. The ſad apprehenſions hereof cauſed me with a weak and trembling hand to draw up this Petition, imploring the aid of God and men, in this our ſinking condition. It was indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be ſent abroad in the world as a deſolate or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, without any diſcovery whence it came, or to whom in particular to apply it ſelf. But after that divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence had ordered the convention of this great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and aſſigned your Honours to bear a part in that truſt, I was eaſily perſwaded to preſume ſo far upon your Chriſtian charity, as to direct it firſt unto your doors, humbly caſting both it, and my ſelf down at your Honours feet, beſeeching you in behalf of the people of this Nation, as the paſſionate Father mentioned in the Goſpel, did our Saviour in behalf of his ſon; If you can<note place="margin">Mark. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> do any thing, have compaſſion on us, and help us. A caſe of higher concernment cannot be preſented unto you,
<pb facs="tcp:115496:3"/>
than this, wherein the honour of Chriſt, and ſalvation of ſo many thouſand ſouls is ingaged. And my hope is, that nothing will be more in your thoughts, than reſtoring beauty to <hi>Sion,</hi> and repairing the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſo ruined every where. They ſeem to me too unreaſonably to debaſe your honourable ſtation, who would exempt the caſe of Chriſt, and the eternal ſalvation of ſouls from your care, leaving onely the petty buſineſſes of this world unto your cognizance; yea to deal moſt injuriouſly with you, perſwading you to neglect that, the care whereof is your greateſt honour, and ſecurity, and the neglect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, would certainly blaſt all your other proceedings.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord vouchſafe to your ſelves, and the reſt of that Honourable Aſſembly, a large portion of that Spirit which he put upon Chriſt, the head of all powers, <hi>A Spirit of wiſdome and underſtanding, of counſel and might,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 2.</note> 
               <hi>of knowledge, and the fear of the Lord,</hi> and make you quick of ſent, in what concerns the honour of Chriſt, the free courſe of his Goſpel, and everlaſting good of the people, and cauſe that all the mountains of difficulties that now lye in your way, may be turned into plains before<note place="margin">Zach. 4. 7.</note> you, that in the end, the languiſhing hopes of the faithful in the land may be revived, the vowed Reformation of Religion accompliſhed, that we, and the following Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations may call you bleſſed, as being under God the happy inſtruments of repairing our breaches, and reſtoring our paths. Which is, and ſhall be the daily prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, and of all that love the Lord Jeſus, a worthleſs ſervant, C. RAIE.</signed>
               <dateline>Waſt. <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 16, 6.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:115496:3"/>
            <head>To all thoſe Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt in the land, whoſe hearts are mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning under the Preſent diſtractions, and breathing after an happy reformation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Fathers and Brethren;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat ſo weak and worthleſſe a creature hath preſumed to ſpeak thus loud in your ears, and by way of petition, to ſuggeſt to your wiſdom; ſome things which will ſcarcely agree with the principles or practice of diverſe, whoſe more eminent piety and learning, hath made them, worthily pretious and honourable in the Churches of Chriſt, I can give no better account, than what <hi>David</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth as forcing words unwillingly from him, <hi>My heart was</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 3</note> 
               <hi>hot within mee, thenſpake I with my tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Principal thing which hath ſtirred theſe paſſions, hath been the Conſideration of the ſad condition wherein the people of this Nation are left, whilſt not alone ſome of their eminent Pilots ſeem to ſit down in diſpair, as if nothing were to bee done in theſe ſtormy times, but onely to pray and wait for a calm, but even diverſe of thoſe, whoſe more induſtrious ſpirits provoke them to action, appear to attend nothing more, but to get with the beſt of their goods unto the boat, leaving the ſhip to ſink in the Sea, contenting themſelves with ſuch a reformation, wherein not alone the viler ſort, whoſe open profaneneſs, and deſperate contempt of God and Religion, proclaimes them unworthy the name or priviledge of Chriſtians, but even the main body and bulk of the people are left, either in the ſtate of abſolute heathens, having none to take any paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb facs="tcp:115496:4"/>
care of their ſouls, or any other priviledge for themſelves or their children, then Jews or Turks might enjoy, if they lived amongſt us, or elſe entertained as ſemi-Chriſtians; neither fully owned nor caſhiered, but wearing by halves the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Of how exceeding dangerous concernment ſuch a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation may prove, ſeems to mee not hard to conjecture, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially being attempted in ſuch a juncture of time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Magiſtrate hath in great part withdrawn his coercive power, as to things of Religion, leaving men to themſelves, and the Devil hath ſo many agents at work, to ſeduce men from the very profeſſion of Chriſt, and to intice them back into the Camp of the enemy.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe this courſe were taken with ſome mutinous or dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous army, that</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The more faithful part of the Souldiery were withdrawn from communion with them.</item>
               <item>2. Their voluntary tenders of renuing their ingagement to their rightful Prince were rejected.</item>
               <item>3. The moſt deſperate mutineirs, who are always ſoliciting a total revolt, were permitted and continued amongſt them. It were eaſy to gueſs what were like ſoon to become of that Army.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The deep apprehenſion of the ſad conſequents of ſuch a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in order to this, and the following generations, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and compared with ſuch remarkable ſigns of divine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, as daily ſound in our ears, hath cauſed mee to forget my former reſolution of ſilence, and how weakly ſo ever, to utter my poor thoughts in this caſe.</p>
            <p>When holy <hi>David</hi> in the height of his zeal, was bringing home the Ark of God to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and found by that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6</note> stroke upon <hi>Vzza,</hi> that ſomwhat was amiſs, and God was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, he is found to have layed aſide, for the preſent, his former deſign, and to have fallen upon a ſerious enquiry; into the cauſe of this diſpleaſure of God, which having wiſely diſcovered; and timely amended, the work at the ſecond attempt went on with happy ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Many of us have as <hi>David</hi> layed out our zeal in bringing the Ark of the Lord, I mean the preſence of Chriſt in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and purity of his worſhip, and Ordinances, home to our
<pb facs="tcp:115496:4"/>
ſelves and our people, but have been inforced to behold ſuch Stumbling of the Oxen, and ſo many of thoſe that have dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Cart, or laied their hands to the Ark, ſuddenly ſmitten either with death, or dreadful fits of quaking and giddineſs, that nothing appears more neceſſarily incumbent on us at this time, than to enter a ſerious ſcrutiny what wee have, done or wherein offended, that God ſhould ſtop our way and brand our work with ſuch evident ſigns of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure?</p>
            <p>Now, as at that time upon ſearch it was found that the grand miſcarriage was, that the Levites had been too favourable to themſelves; ſpared their own ſhoulders too much, having found out an eaſier way to carry the Ark than God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, making that the burden of Oxen, which ſhould have<note place="margin">1 Chron. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12, 13, &amp;c.</note> been born by themſelves. So I cannot but fear that ſomething equivalent may bee found amongſt us at this time. We have too much indulged our ſelves, declined the labour impoſed by Chriſt, and found out eaſier ways to carry the Ark, than his commands will allow.</p>
            <p>To cull out a few of the beſt of the people, or whoſe wayes and principles do moſt ſuit with our own, theſe to new dip in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, new name them a Church, or to admit onely them to a full communion with us in ordinances, leaving the reſt of the people to wander as ſheep in the mountains, affording them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advantage of Sacraments to ingage them to Chriſt, nor cenſures to awaken them out of their luſts, is a farre eaſier task, than by vehement indeavours, both publike and private to bring back and ingage the body of the people to Chriſt, and ſtrenuouſly to draw forth the cenſures by him committed unto us, in revenge of all the ſtubbornneſs and diſobedience of thoſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 6 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. 18. 15</note> who ſhall contemn ſuch applications as he hath appointed for their recovery.</p>
            <p>Now the former of theſe, as being much more facile and eaſy, hath (though under ſeveral and different formes) been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by many of us; but the latter, as much more painful and burdenſome, We have either totally ſhunned, or performed by halves.</p>
            <p>Now if upon examination it ſhould bee found, that this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned way of reformation under what form ſo ever attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:115496:5"/>
is no way approved by Chriſt, but a meer invention of man, to eaſe our ſelves of the burden which it belongs to the Miniſters of God to go under; Wee ſhall then ſee no cauſe to admire that God hath erected ſo many monuments of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and cauſed a <hi>Perez Uzza</hi> to bee written in ſo many places.</p>
            <p>How dangerous the leaſt miſtake in things of this nature is, both the caſe under our hands, and likewiſe that of <hi>Nadab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dev. 10</note> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> do ſufficiently witneſſe, but when the miſcarriage is ſuch as may bee rationally thought to indanger the loſſe of many thouſand ſouls, bought by the bloud of the Lord, and ingaged in Covenant with him, yea the very undoing this and the following Generations; by diſſolving the bonds betwixt Chriſt and this Nation, it cannot ſeem ſtrange if God for one at that time, doth now erect many Pillars of Salt, and as any party hath travelled further in theſe wayes, ſo the notes of his wrath bee ſound more ſignal on them.</p>
            <p>Now that the way before mentioned, notwithſtanding ſome ſhew of piety, in making or preſerving a purity in Churches, or Ordinances; Yet truly is no way appointed by Chriſt, but like the new Cart made for the Ark at that time, a meer invention of man to eaſe our ſelves of the burden, I cannot but vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſpect upon theſe following grounds, which I humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to your grave and mature conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe I finde not in Scripture, either precept or preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for any ſuch way of Reformation, though caſes not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to ours, have often happened of old. Many revolts and backſlidings of Gods people ſtand upon record in Scripture with the ways and means of their recovery, but this way of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the more eminently pious into new ſocieties, or the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the ingaging ſeales of the Covenant from the People, when willing to renue their ingagement, I never fixde recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture. But on the contrary, thoſe men whoſe names are pretious in the book of God, for the glorious Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations made in their dayes, as <hi>Aſa, Hezekiah, Joſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 35.</note> &amp;c. are plainly found to have made it their great deſign, to bring back and ingage the body of the people to God, and for that purpoſe to have attended nothing more earneſtly, than to bind them in ſacramental bonds to the Lord. Neither doth the
<pb facs="tcp:115496:5"/>
Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in order to the Churches of <hi>Corinth</hi> or <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſadly corrupted, perſwade either the ſounder part to ſeparate themſelves into new Churches, or the Paſtors to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Sacraments from them till better reformed, but on the<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 10 1 Cor. 10. 21.</note> contrary earneſtly, preſſeth Love and Union amongſt them, and maketh advantage of their Sacramental ingagements to Chriſt, to diſ-ingage them from their ſinful corruptions.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Neither do I know how to reconcile theſe proceedings with the glorious promiſes contained in Scripture, of the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of the Church, or Kingdome of Chriſt in theſe Goſpel times. Nothing ſeems more pregnant in the Prophets, than<note place="margin">Iſa. 2. 2</note> that the times of the Meſſiah, ſhould bee times of great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to the Church, by flowing in of Nations to it. Now if we well conſider how ſmall a part of the World is at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or for many ages by paſt, hath been Chriſtians, and<note place="margin">Breerw. p. 118</note> how ſmall a part of the Chriſtian world, is ſo Orthodox in opinion, or regular in practice, as the body of the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, wee muſt needs conclude, that if ſuch as theſe be ſecluded, and a gathering made according to the mind of ſome of the ſtricter ſort of our brethren, the Church of Chriſt would now bee brought into much narrower bounds, than before the manifeſtation of Chriſt in the fleſh; when I conſider the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter roll given in by <hi>Joab</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> I am inforced to think the<note place="margin">1 Chron. 21. 5</note> Church at that time did not conſiſt of leſs than five or ſix milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Souls, &amp; thoſe (doubtleſſe) much augmented in <hi>Salomons</hi> dayes, but ſhould none bee owned as Church members, but ſuch as ſome of our Brethren aforeſaid would admit, I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether the whole Chriſtian world at this day, would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a tenth of that number, neither have many ages ſince the manifeſtation of Chriſt in the fleſh, been much happier than ours in the number of Orthodox Chriſtians; ſo as whilſt theſe ſeparating wayes ſeem to aim at the honour of Chriſt, in leaving none but precious ſtones in his building, they are found much to detract from his honour in another way, namely in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridging<note place="margin">Prov. 14. 28</note> ſo much the number of his ſubjects.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Neither do I know how to make theſe ſtricter proceedings agree with the infinite grace &amp; indulgence of God ſo much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in Scripture, and ſo often proved in his compaſſionate<note place="margin">Exod. 34. 6</note> owning thoſe that were once entred into Covenant with him,
<pb facs="tcp:115496:6"/>
even then, when their dreadfull revolts and manifold whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,<note place="margin">Jer. 3. 1</note> did ſeem to cry aloud for a Bill of divorce. Now the people whoſe caſe I am pleading, are certainly entred into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, being given up to him in the Sacram ent of Baptiſme, and notwithſtanding many miſcarriages, are not found to have renounced this Covenant, they truly beleeve the fundamental Articles of our holy Religion, and even in their greateſt extremities, when they are leaſt like to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, make profeſſion thereof; ſo as they muſt of neceſſity be accounted Beleevers, not Infidels, men within, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, according to the language of Scripture: Now how the rejecting theſe men, by hundreds and thouſands, as if they were heathen, or debarring them from the Ordinances of Chriſt, unleſs upon their contumacious rejecting ſuch applications as he hath appointed, will ſtand with this infinite grace and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of God, I cannot conceive.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The ſingular love and goodneſs of Chriſt, doth inforce to beleeve, that in his kingdome, <hi>ſalus populi,</hi> is <hi>lex ſuprema.</hi> That the Ordinances were made for man, not man for the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and conſequently that ſuch ways as for preſerving the purity of Ordinances, ſhould deſtroy the ſouls of the people, can be no ways approved by Chriſt, now whether theſe wayes of withdrawing the more devout and zealous part, from their communion, leaving them to wander in the wilderneſſe as ſheep without Shepheards, ſtaving them off from renuing their ingagements to Chriſt in that heart-melting Sacrament, be not deſtructive to the ſouls of the people, creating in them hard and uncharitable thoughts concerning the more eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pious, leaving them under the guilt of a dreadful ſin of omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and hindering them from one ſpecial means of recovering ſtrength againſt their corruptions, ſeems not hard to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. For mine own part, I cannot but ſtrongly conceive in this caſe, what <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſpeaks in another, that diverſe of us have by our unadviſed zeal hindred the people, and that a farre greater ſlaughter might have been made amongſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14. 30</note> of God, had the people been permitted more freely to taſte this heavenly food.</p>
            <p n="5">5 When I conſider this way of proceeding, in order to people wherein they are excluded, from communion in Sacraments, and in the mean time, admitted to their wonted communion,
<pb facs="tcp:115496:6"/>
in prayers, praiſes, humiliations, &amp;c. I cannot finde that clearneſs of Scripture, evidence for this halving in point of communion, that ſhould warrant our faith to expect the preſence or bleſſing of Chriſt upon ſuch kind of cenſures; I have according to my poor ability, conſidered what hath been publiſhed by ſome reverend Brethren in defence of ſuſpenſions, but am inforced ſtill to conceive, that the communion of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians one with another, lyeth as truly (though peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with ſome gradual difference) in prayer, as in breaking of Bread; and that the vaſt difference that now wee have<note place="margin">Act. 2. 42</note> made, admitting all to communion in one, and ſo few in the other, was never learned from the rules or examples in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor yet from the practice of the Primitive Church, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jewiſh or Chriſtian, and conſequently that if wee will bring up our cenſures to the rules and patterns aforeſaid, wee muſt remove the rail from the communion table, and ſet it nearer the door of the Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Were theſe ſuſpenſions never ſo clearly proved by Scripture, yet it ſeems juſtly queſtionable, whether Chriſtian prudence guided by Scripture-light, will admit them to be ſo generally paſſed. Eccleſiaſtical cenſures ſeem to bee enervate, and looſe much of their vigor, when they fall upon the major part of the People, yea more to reſemble ſome Popiſh interdict, than the cenſures of Chriſt, the tender Phyſitian; when a finger, an hand, or an arm is dangerouſly diſeaſed, the wiſe Chirurgion ſometimes thinks of cutting it off, but he would ſcarce bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved as a good Chirurgion, who ſhould deal thus with the major part of the body, though affected in the ſame manner. The bleſſed Apoſtle ſaw ſeveral perſons in the Churches of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> whoſe caſe hee bewailes, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture might think them worthy of cenſure, yet at preſent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 21 1 Cor. 6. 1 Cor. 5 Gal. 5. 12</note> out only one not orious offender in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and wiſhes that only the ring-leaders of error in the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſhould bee cut off. Now had we taken this courſe to admit more generally the body of the People to a full commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and laid ſome ſtubborn notorious offenders, under more ſignal remarkable cenſures, peradventure we might have ſeen ſome more happy effects of our proceedings, than now we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115496:7"/>I have thus preſumed according to the licentiouſneſs of theſe times, to utter my mournful thoughts in this caſe, craving from you a candid interpretation of my meaning, though you finde my words rude and unpoliſht. And if it ſhall happen that any of you ſhall mee in opinion concerning theſe things, let this poor Petition have the help of your Prayers, that it may finde entertainment in the hearts of thoſe to whom it is directed: if otherwiſe, let the Author obtain the benefit of them, that God will bee pleaſed graciouſly to pardon all his errors and ſinful miſcarriages, who, if he knoweth his own heart, would willingly ſee and ſubmit to the mind of the Lord, though never ſo croſſing to his former opinion or practice.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Waſt. Septemb. 1656</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115496:7"/>
            <head>To all that love and ſerve the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the work of <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> or <hi>Miniſtry.</hi> As alſo to all the more eminent Profeſſors of Religion within this Commonwealth.</head>
            <head type="sub">A mournful Complaint, and Supplication, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of many Thouſands of the more weak and ignorant people of this Nation; Humbly lamenteth and declareth,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat notwithſtanding your poor Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners have even by your confeſſion, reaſonable and immortal Souls, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of eternal bliſs or miſery, notwithſtanding the ſame common nature, and the many civil bonds wherein we ſtand related unto you, notwithſtanding you ſee us weakly owning the ſame God, the ſame Chriſt, the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles of Religion with your ſelves, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you ſee us dreadfully aſſaulted by the power and policie of the ſame enemies with whom you are in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; notwithſtanding you behold our danger from thoſe enemies in regard of our ignorance and weakneſs to bee ſo great and imminent, that were we not too inſenſible,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115496:8"/>
we ſhould even fill heaven and earth with our ſhrikes and cryes, yea notwithſtanding you profeſs your ſelves Diſciples and followers of the Lord Jeſus, who not alone deſcended from heaven, and gave his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood a ranſome for ſuch poore creatures as we, but whilſt he was here upon earth, did with moſt earneſt and unweariable pains, ſeek up ſuch feeble and wandring ſheep, and moſt ſweetly communicate himſelf unto them.</p>
            <p>Yet the depth of our preſent miſery, proclaimeth aloud, that you are extremely ſtraitned in your bowels of compaſſion towards us, in that we remain under ſo much ignorance and blindneſs, under ſo much deadneſs and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality, and you no more forcibly apply your ſelves unto our help; you ſee us groping and taſping as blinde men in danger to fall into the pit, and you cry not out unto us, you ſee us ſhattered and overpowred by the cruel enemy, and you haſten not unto reſcue, you ſee us fallen amongſt Theeves, and lye wounded in the wayes, and you paſs by on the other ſide, nor powring oyl or wine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our wounds yea you ſee many of us panting, and ready to breathe out the laſt gaſp of our dying Chriſtianity, and you bring no cordials to revive us.</p>
            <p>You have made high profeſſions for promoting the work of Chriſt in this Generation, you have taken deep ingagements upon your ſelves to endeavour a glorious reformation, and we hope ſome others have found ſome more comfortable fruits from thoſe profeſſions, but alſo we for our parts are inforced ſadly to look back on for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times and ſay, <hi>O that it were with us as in the dayes of old!</hi> ſeeing that little knowledge we had of Chriſt is now diminiſhed, our ſmall heat of love abated, our weak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that our dear Saviour almoſt quite obliterate, and our children like to be ſet in a more hopeleſs condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than our ſelves.</p>
            <p>We cannot deny, but as God hath been infinitly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in calling us by the preaching of his Goſpel to the knowledge of his Son, ſo with, and under you, we have enjoyed thoſe bleſſed advantages, by many godly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115496:8"/>
and exhortations, that if we had not been wanting to our ſelves, we might have attained much more under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the things of God, and greater victories againſt thoſe corruptions, that now ſo overpower us: But as the Patient, who hath contracted diſeaſes by his own folly, or careleſneſs, yet expecteth that the tender-hearted Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, ſhould faithfully apply himſelf unto the cure, ſo we being miſerably wounded and infeebled by our own ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſs, yet have hope, that you who behold our dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful condition, and whoſe place and office binds you to bee healers, will have your bowels yerning towards us; and upon this our mournful complaint will lay out your ſelves with greater induſtry and diligence in order to our recovery.</p>
            <p>But becauſe we would willingly move your moſt tender compaſſions, we ſhal humbly caſt our ſelves down at the feet of each of you in particular, and ſpread our mournful caſe before you, wiſhing that our deep ſighs and groans, might fill your ears, but if that do not, that yet your eyes might affect your hearts in beholding our moſt ſad and lamentable ſtate.</p>
            <p>O you the Magiſtrates! who poſſeſs the name and place of Gods amongſt us, in whoſe power, and at whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are all the external means of our preſent and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting welfare, upon whoſe directions and commands, our eyes wait even in thoſe things which concern our ſouls, and eternal being.</p>
            <p>You have the command of our perſons and eſtates, to order and diſpoſe them at your pleaſure, you have the command of our Schools and Univerſities to fill or empty them, you have the command of our Paſtors and Teachers, to place or remove them, you have the command of our Churches and Chappels to ſhut or open them, you have the command of our Tythes and other Oblations, to give or diſpoſe them to whom you pleaſe: And ſurely nothing ſhould be dearer to you than the glory of him from whom you have received this power, and the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſouls by Chriſt committed to your truſt.</p>
            <p>Now unto you our mournful condition lamentably
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115496:9"/>
complaineth, that diverſe of our Pariſhes are left wholly deſtitute of Miniſters, there is none to lead us in the wayes of God, none to break the bread of life unto us, no not ſo much as to read the holy Scriptures in our Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the wayes of <hi>Sion</hi> mourn becauſe none come to her ſolemn Aſſemblies; <hi>We, and our children faint for thirſt, and there is none to draw the living waters for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That divers of our Churches are ſtill poſſeſſed by weak, ignorant, or ſcandalous Miniſters, who either through unskilfulneſs, or unfaithfulneſs betray our ſouls into the hands of our enemies, and that you neither have removed them, nor injoyned them to read plainly to us the holy Scriptures, and other godly Prayers, and Sermons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by abler men, which advantage our Fathers did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in the penury of learned Miniſters, and which our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience aſſures us, would be far more profitable for us than ſuch Prayers and Sermons as are of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing.</p>
            <p>That you have placed in many of our Churches, and given the Tythes, and other profits belonging to the cure of ſouls, to men that refuſe to take any ſuch charge upon them, and who are ſo far from having the affections, or performing the duties of faithful Paſtors to us, that they do profeſledly diſ-own any ſuch relation, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the duties thereunto belonging, thence they neither baptiſe nor catechiſe our children, nor do they adminiſter the Lords Supper in our Congregations, our ſick and feeble perſons they viſit not, nor own it as a duty incumbent on them to take care for our ſouls.</p>
            <p>And though indeed they make Orations in our Pulpits, yet for as much as they profeſs themſelves, no Officers or Meſſengers of Chriſt unto us, we cannot hear them as his Miniſters, and conſequently cannot expect his preſence with them, or bleſſing on their labours.</p>
            <p>That you do not according to the noble example of <hi>Aſa, Joſiah,</hi> and other holy Governors, inforce us by your Authority, to worſhip the only true God, and to attend his ſacred Ordinances, you take us indeed off from our wonted labour on the Lords dayes, but do not likewiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115496:9"/>
compel us to attend ſome publick Aſſemblies to hear the word of God read, or preached to us, we as idle Schollars refuſe to go to School, and you our Maſters rebuke us not: This indulgence of yours we finde indeed pleaſing to the fleſh, which would rather ſleep or play, or drink at home, than go to Church to worſhip Chriſt, but we fear that many of us will finde cauſe for ever to curſe our ſelves for taking, and you for giving us this woful li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>That you commend not to us by your Authority ſome publick Confeſsion of Faith to be learned and owned by us, which might be as a touchſtone to try the Doctrines which we hear, and a preſervative againſt the curſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of thoſe men, that ſeek to raſe the foundations of our holy Religion; for as the Creed, the Lords Prayer, and ten Commandements, many of us have quite forgotten them, ſeldome or never hearing any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them in our Churches.</p>
            <p>That you do not injoyn a more reverend, and ſeemly deportment of the body in our publick Aſſemblies wee finde all helps and advantages, too little to raiſe our drouſie hearts to true devotion, but when we are inforced to behold the rude and unreverent carriage of others in our Congregations, we find that it mightily hinders and abates the intention and devotion of our ſpiritis in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; nor can we think that you would well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſuch rudeneſs and diſorder in mens addreſſes to your ſelves.</p>
            <p>That you aſſign no more Miniſters to our greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, many thouſands of us ſometimes have but one (if one) to lead us in our ſpiritual welfare: In your civil wars where the enemies are leſs dangerous, you have many Officers for every hundred men, And can you think that one man is ſufficient to inſtruct, exerciſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct many thouſands againſt a more ſubtil, vigilant, and formidable enemy?</p>
            <p>That you have appointed no means to diſcover who are liſted as our fellow-ſouldiers under Chriſt in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſm, which we ſuſpect will leave no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115496:10"/>
ſmall ſcruple upon our children, and others when we are gone, if by the infinite mercies of God, Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhould ſtill be continued in this Nation, you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the Diptyches, or books of Record out of the hands of our Miniſters, and put them into other hands, but not injoyned them to record the baptiſm of any, which giveth occaſion to adverſaries to think that you ſet but little price upon that ſacred Ordinance.</p>
            <p>That you have let looſe ſo many ravening Wolves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, who go up and down ſeeking to devour, venting their poyſonous ſoul-deſtroying errors, both publickly and privately, whereby we the more ignorant are often ſhaken in the very fundamentals of our holy Religion, and left in doubt what we ſhould beleeve, how much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were it for us if you ſuffered men to poyſon and infect our bodies to the deſtruction of this our life natural, than thus to poyſon our ſouls to the evident hazzard of our everlaſting ruine.</p>
            <p>Conſider we beſeech you, our ignorance, and weakneſs, and have compaſſion on our ſouls, and let it appear by the intention of your care and watchfulneſs in order to our ſpiritual good, that our Governors are real Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and know the worth of that which Chriſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at ſo dear a rate, that he may own you as his faithful ſtewards and we may bleſs God for you as tender nurſing Fathers unto us.</p>
            <p>O you the Miniſters of Chriſt! whom he hath ſet as watchmen to diſcover dangers, and give warning as Captains, and Leaders in his Army, as Stewards in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſy to give to every one his portion in due ſeaſon; you are ſet to be the Lights of the world, the Salt of the earth, yea Clouds to diſtil the precious dews upon us; from you we expect not alone directions from your heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but light from your graceful walking, ſtrength from your ſervent prayer, and ſweet refreſhings from your fatherly compaſſions, that you in imitation of the great Shepherd, ſhould carry the Lambs in the boſome of your love, and gently lead the feeble of the flock.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115496:10"/>And bleſſed bee God amongſt you, wee have found ſome truly loving and compaſſionate Samaritans, who have pittied us in our diſtreſs, have bound up our wounds, and layed out your ſelves to the utmoſt of your ſtrength for our eternal comfort; for whoſe faithfulneſs in order to our ſouls, we hope many of us ſhall celebrate the name of God with everlaſting praiſes.</p>
            <p>But againſt many of you, our doleful caſe mournfully declareth, that notwithſtanding the holineſſe of your fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the great truſt by Chriſt committed to you, yet you ſeem careleſſe and regardleſſe of our immortal ſoules; more minding your own temporal advantage in the world, than the eternal condition of the people committed to your charge, incumbring your ſelves ſo much with worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that you cannot give attendance to reading, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and to doctrin, and whilſt you have left your watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tower, and are buſy in thoſe lower vallies, the enemy, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies vigilant for miſchief, ſurprizeth us to the eternall hazzard of ſouls.</p>
            <p>That divers of you perform the work belonging to your high Calling, with ſo much coldneſs and remiſneſs, that you occaſion us to queſtion whether you bee in good earneſt, or do your ſelves beleeve what you deliver unto us, our houſes are on fire, and you knock ſoftly at our doors, a dreadful deafneſſe is upon us, and you whiſper in our cars, our neceſſities require that you ſhould cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud and lift up your voices like trumpets, to make known to us our ſin and danger, and you ſpeak with ſo low a voice as it you were afraid to wake us.</p>
            <p>That you attend no more to the ſure laying the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of religion in our hearts, by frequent catechizing, and plain Preaching the fundamentals, clearing up to us the grounds upon which theſe great things of eternity are to be owned by us, through ignorance of theſe your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, though otherwiſe excellent, are made in great part unprofitable to us, you are upon the finiſhing whilſt wee ſtick at the foundation, you read in a manner all your lectures to Schollers, of the higher form; whilſt wee the more ignorant are neglected as not being able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115496:11"/>
the terms in which theſe great things of God are by you delivered to us.</p>
            <p>That ſome of you deny unto your children the ſacred body of our Chriſtian profeſſion, the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, wee would bring our Children in our Arms, and preſent them unto Chriſt for his Bleſſing, but you thruſt us back; we would ingage our Children unto Chriſt, to live and dye his ſervants, but you will not permit us, but inforce us to leave them free, to ſerve the Devil if they pleaſe, as if you had conſpired with our enemies to thruſt our poſterity back again to Heatheniſm.</p>
            <p>That many of you permit us not to celebrate the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of our dying Saviour in the Sacrament of his laſt Supper, and ſo deprive our ſouls of that heavenly food, that our dear Lord hath with ſo much coſt provided for us, wee would after many ſad violations renew our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Chriſt, and ingage our ſouls more firmly to him, but you will not permit us; You complain of the looſneſſe of our ſpirits, whilſt you withhold the bonds that ſhould knit us faſter unto Chriſt; you complain of our weakneſs in reſiſting corruptions, whilſt you withhold the food whereby wee ſhould bee ſtrengthned; you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Schiſm, ſtrife, and diviſion, whilſt by you the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Pledge of union is detained from us.</p>
            <p>Some of you have for many years wholly laid aſide this Sacred Ordinance, chuſing rather to deprive your ſelves and others, whom you better approve, of this heavenly banquet, then to afford it unto us; you complain of ſome of us for living in known ſinnes; and frequently make your proof from ſome neglect of duty, whilſt you your ſelves have lived many years in the notorious omiſſion of this great duty, ſo ſolemnly injoyned by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Others of you, though you do adminiſter this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you have raiſed ſo many ſtoppes, and made ſuch lofty rails about the table, that few of us can come unto it, as if you thought it a matter of great piety, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the tenders of the body and bloud of Chriſt into a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row room, and cauſe thoſe his bitter paſſions ſuffered for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115496:11"/>
mankinde to be known and remembred onely by a few, as if it were an honour to Chriſt, or advantage to the world, that his name and memorial ſhould periſh from the hearts and mouths of ſo great a part of the people pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing his name, and ingaged in Covenant to him.</p>
            <p>Hence many of you are ſo far from inviting us to this heavenly banquet, that you do by your preaching and otherwiſe, continually hinder and diſcourage us; as if wee were of our ſelves too forward to worſhip Chriſt, and keep up his memorial; aggravating to the height, if not beyond the truth, the danger if we come unworthily, but not equally acquainting us, with the like or greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the total neglect of this great Command of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Others of you, have erected a Court of ruling Elders, and ſet up them to be Judges over us, and that not in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to any crime or accuſation brought againſt us, but to examine us in order to the Sacrament, without whoſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, we may not be admitted to the portion of our Maſters food, and have not pittied us in our infirmities, when you ſaw us in our ignorance, jealous of new erected powers, and that we would hardly be convinced, that the buſineſs of Sacraments did belong to any other but preaching Elders, yea that we could hardly own them for Elders, upon whom we ſaw no ſtamp of God by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to that Office, nor character of humane power by Commiſſion from the Magiſtrate, or by any legal choice or election from the people.</p>
            <p>Others of you have combined your ſelves with ſome ſmall parties of our neighbours, and thoſe ſometimes whoſe private waies and principles we cannot own, and have called theſe your Church, and ſet up thoſe to bee Judges over us, according to whoſe ſentence, and that without any legal trial, we may, or may not be admitted to our Maſters Table, not ſhewing us which way this power over us ſhould be derived unto them, or giving us cauſe to beleeve that you, or they would willingly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bee ſo dealt withall by us, or any <hi>minor</hi> party amongſt your ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115496:12"/>By theſe, and the like means you have diſcouraged and diſheartned us from coming to this heavenly Banquet, and kept us ſo long faſting, that our ſtomachs are almoſt wholly gone, and our ſpirits much infeebled, and we fear a dreadful guilt is contracted by our not coming to this ſacred feaſt, remembring how terrible Gods threatnings were againſt thoſe that came not to his Paſſeover of old,<note place="margin">Numb. 9. 13.</note> and wiſh it may not be laid to your charge that you have ſo many waies hindred and diſcouraged us.</p>
            <p>Conſider we beſeech you, your dealings in this caſe, and compare your practice with the rules and preſidents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in holy Scripture for our inſtruction, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve whether the ſervants and officers of Chriſt, there mentioned, did deal with the people of their times as you have dealth with us.</p>
            <p>We are indeed guilty of much ignorance and carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the Lord humble and amend us; But do you indeed think, that there was none in the Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under <hi>Moſes,</hi> as ignorant and carnal as we? And did <hi>Moſes</hi> uſe ſuch means to ſtave off them from coming to the Paſſeover, as you have done to hinder us?</p>
            <p>Was there never a one in <hi>Iſrael</hi> or <hi>Judah</hi> in the daies<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.</note> of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> that had as little knowledge, or appearance of real godlineſs as we, when that holy King ſent out his general ſummons, <hi>Come to the houſe of God at Jeruſalem, and keep a Paſſeover to the Lord God of Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was there none in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> beſides that one inceſtuous perſon, againſt whom as juſt exceptions might have been made, as againſt us, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> maketh<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 16.</note> uſe of their joynt communion at the Lords Table to preſs their non-communion at the Idols Temple?</p>
            <p>What do you think of the Diſciples of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, were they free from ignorance and carnality, or<note place="margin">Luke 18. 34. &amp; 22. 24.</note> was there not a dreadful cloud of ignorance and carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity upon their ſpirits at that very time, when they were by Chriſt himſelf admitted to this ſacred Banquet?</p>
            <p>Yea what Officer of Chriſt did you ever read of in holy Scripture, that ſecluded any from Paſſeover, or Supper, unleſs ſuch deſperate and notorious ſinners, as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115496:12"/>
were likewiſe ſecluded from communion in all other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>If theſe things move you not, conſider (we beſeech you) your own practice, and compare your dealing in this, with your other adminiſtrations, and ſee how you will vindicate your ſelves from contradictions.</p>
            <p>We hear you ſometimes in your Sermons ſweetly ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Chriſt to all that be willing to receive him, earneſtly inviting us to come to Chriſt, telling us that Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth no worthineſs on our parts, but onely a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to accept him tendred to us, but when upon theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitations we come unto you, and profeſs our willingneſs to accept the Lord Jeſus Chriſt tendred in that holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, having no other way wherein we can ſo viſibly yeeld obedience to your invitations, you thruſt us back, and tell us we muſt not come, becauſe we are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
            <p>We finde you in your publick prayer owning us bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, Saints<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and faithful, as appears in that you do not alone in communion with us, but can in our name, as our mouth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> call God Father, Chriſt Mediator, and tender up moſt ſpiritual confeſſions, petitions and thankſgivings unto God; but when we would with you approach unto the ſame God and Mediator in the holy Sacrament, you quite diſclaim this brother-hood, in prayer acknowledged, and alledge againſt our coming to it, That you muſt not give holy things to dogs or ſwine.</p>
            <p>Yea ſome of you, when wee preſent our children to Baptiſm, require from us a profeſſion of our repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance for ſin, and faith in the Lord Jeſus, and upon ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion by us made, do baptize our children, and juſtifie your practiſe againſt thoſe that do oppoſe you, upon this account that our children are holy, being the off-ſpring of beleevers, and yet when we would come to preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt our ſelves to the Lord in the other Sacrament, you refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and ſtave us off as unholy and unbeleevers.</p>
            <p>In all acts of civil converſe where the greateſt danger of contagion from polluted perſons is, and which the<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Scripture moſt expreſly forbideth with ſcandalous Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115496:13"/>
you neither warn others, nor do you your ſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline communion with us; you eat and drink with us, at your own, ours, and other mens tables, and that without ſcruple, ſo far as we perceive, and yet when we would up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the command of Chriſt, come and preſent our ſelves with you at our Maſters Table, you ſeem to fear contagion from us, and alledge againſt us that of the Apoſtle, <hi>With ſuch a one, no not to eat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How your greater wiſdome will accord theſe things, we know not, but to us the more ignorant, they appear little leſs than contradictions, and leave us in a ſtrange amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſidering what thoughts you have of us, or would have us to have of our ſelves, whilſt in ſome things you ſo ſweetly own us as brethren, and good Chriſtians, in others, ſo ſtrangely caſt us off as Dogs or Swine.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot think you have entertained the Popiſh doctrin of a real or corporal preſence of Chriſt in this Ordinance, more than in the reſt, and yet we cannot but wonder in what School you have learned to make this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Chriſts Ordinances, that all the reſidue ſhould be laid in common, and onely the Communion table railed in.</p>
            <p>Wee indeed hear this often alleadged, that other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are converting, this only confirming; other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are inſtrumental to beget ſouls to Chriſt, this only to nouriſh thoſe that are begotten: Now though it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to us very hard to affirm that that Ordinance wherein there is a tender of Chriſt the principle of life unto the ſoul, may not be a means of conveighing life, even the firſt motions of life ſupernatural to the ſoul, yet were this diſtinction uſed onely to difference the Sacrament from the preaching of the word, we could more eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it; but when wee finde it likewiſe uſed to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it from Prayer, and other the like Ordinances, it quite ſurpaſſeth our ſhallow underſtanding to conceive the reaſon of it, conſidering wee finde by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tim. 2. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jam. 1. 6 Rom. 10. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> that repentance and faith are neceſſarily required in order to Prayer, as well as to the Sacrament, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115496:13"/>
aſſures us, that a child muſt be born before it cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as well as live before it eateth.</p>
            <p>But what ever difference your wiſdome can finde out between this and other Ordinances, ſure we are, that by this means it is come to paſſe that your cenſures, if thoſe your ſuſpenſions bee accounted ſuch, are made in great part fruſtrate, and invalid in order to thoſe ends for which our Lord Chriſt hath appointed cenſures in his Church, as having little or no power to ſhame, and conſequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the offender, or to preſerve the ſounder part from contagion; for how is any man like to bee made aſhamed who injoyeth full communion with the beſt, excepting in one Ordinance, and hath ſo many and ſome ſo honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companions with him in the want of that? or how is the ſounder part like to be preſerved, whilſt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe familiarly with contagious perſons, excepting in one Ordinance, and that one, wherein of all others, there uſed to be the leaſt evaporation of corruption?</p>
            <p>If theſe things yet move you not, let us intreat you to behold the countenances of your poor people, and if you find us more fair and fat in fleſh ſince this reſtraint of yours than when we did eat our portion of the Kings meat, then you may ſtill detain it from us, but if you ſee apparently, that we are grown leaner and more feeble, yea have more grievous and noyſome ſpots and biles ariſing upon us, then have pity on us, and reſtore unto us the portion of food detained from us, yea have pity on your ſelves, and think what anſwer you will make unto the King, when he ſhall pleaſe to look upon us.</p>
            <p>O conſider (we beſeech you) the ſad caſe of your poor people! and inſtead of theſe unprofitable, and as wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive unſcriptural ſuſpenſions, make more forcible appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to us, teaching, exhorting, and admoniſhing with all earneſtneſs, not alone publikely, but from houſe to houſe, according to that noble pattern of St. <hi>Paul:</hi> make<note place="margin">Act. 20. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> known to us, the true nature of this Ordinance, and how ſtrong an obligation, it layeth upon us of obedience to Chriſt, whoſe ſervants we there profeſs our ſelves, and then with holy <hi>Hezekiah</hi> call us to ingage our ſelves to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115496:14"/>
the Lord in this ſacred Ordinance, and prove whether this will not be more effectual to recover us from ſin, and ſave our ſouls, than theſe your ſuſpenſions have been.</p>
            <p>And if you finde amongſt our number, ſome whoſe ignorance is ſo groſs, or ſcandal ſo notorious, that you dare not but lay us under cenſures; yet let thoſe cenſures be inflicted in the way preſcribed by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and let all your further proceedings with us bee accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rules of holy Scripture, that both you, and wee may expect his bleſſing in all your dealings with us.</p>
            <p>Let thoſe more private and publick admonitions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned<note place="margin">Matth. 18. 15.</note> by our Saviour, go before your cenſures, and prove whether he will not bleſs theſe to our emendation, if after all ſuch Chriſtian applications made to us, we go on boldly, and contumaciouſly in ſin, wee then plead no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for our ſelves, if you cenſure us more deeply than a bare ſuſpenſion from the Sacrament amounteth unto: but till this be done, and we found obſtinate, do not deprive us of the food by our Lord, provided for us, nor us of that precious opportunity of ingaging our ſouls more firmly unto him.</p>
            <p>Make ſome difference (wee beſeech you) between us, though many wayes faulty, and thoſe that are deſperate contemners of God, and all Religion, remembring that there are wandring ſheep, as well as dogs and ſwine, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Chriſtians, and brethren walking diſorderly, as well as ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> mentioned in Scripture: that there were<note place="margin">Numb. 15. 30.</note> many in the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that did ſin through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance, beſides thoſe daring preſumptuous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from whom the Lord would have no ſacrifice: Now if you acknowledge ſuch a difference, conſider whether it be not more agreeable to the tender mercies of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to receive ſuch weaklings in the faith as we, amongſt the better ſort, by whoſe godly counſels, and example, we may be edified, than to leave us amongſt the deſperate contemners of God, and all Religion, by their curſed counſels and examples to be eternally ruined and deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115496:14"/>O lay to heart the dreadful charge of God againſt his Paſtors of old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the diſeaſed you have not ſtrengthened, neither have you healed that which was ſick, you have<note place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. 34. 44.</note> not bound up that which was broken, neither have you brought back that which was driven away, or ſought up that which was loſt.</p>
            <p>O remember that you are Officers under him, who hath profeſſed hee will not break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax, and who deſpiſeth not the day of ſmall things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O! let your compaſſions imitate the mercies of him, whoſe name you bear, and ſay you concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 8.</note> our numerous cluſter, though it be not pleaſing to the eye deſtroy it not, there is a bleſſing in it.</p>
            <p>O you the more eminent profeſſors of Religion! you have by the advantage of more excellent natural endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, better education, greater diligence, or more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant grace from above, far ſurpaſſed us in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding, in ſpiritual things, you have made a more glorious profeſſion of Religion, and have clean eſcaped ſome of thoſe pollutions in which we are yet miſerably intangled, you as Schollers of the higheſt form, are inabled to afford much help to us, who are of the loweſt in the School of Chriſt, and divine providence hath ſo diſperſed you amongſt us in your habitations, and cauſed ſuch mutual intercourſe of worldly buſineſſe that you have much advantage to diſcover our infirmities, and afford a ſeaſonable ſupply of help and ſupport unto us.</p>
            <p>And bleſſed bee God amongſt your number, wee have found ſome humble, charitable, and truly ſelf-denying Chriſtians, who have cheerfully laid out themſelves, and their ſeveral abilities for our good and comfort: for whoſe faithfulneſs in order to our ſouls, wee are bound always to be thankful, and although ſometimes through the prevalency of our corruptions, wee too much ſlight their gracious counſel and advice, yet when our ſpirits are more ſerious, wee remember feelingly their godly admonitions, and eſteem them the moſt faithful of our friends.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115496:15"/>But againſt many of you our mournful condition ſadly complaineth, that you have ſhut up the bowels of your compaſſions from us, that you look aloofe upon us, and proclaim us blind and miſerable, but do not ſtrongly apply your ſelves unto our help, you ſee us in imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to fall into the pit, but take little care to keep us out, you ſee us worryed and much overpowered by our luſts, but haſten not to our aſſiſtance, you ſee us chilled with cold, and you rub us not, many of you think it enough to ſlip away; and ſhut up your ſelves in ſome ſeparate Congregations, leaving us in danger to periſh in our coldneſſe, or bee devoured by the cruel Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>Yea though you proclaim us blind and ignorant, yet you ceaſe not to caſt many fearful ſtumbling blocks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, whilſt wee are inforced to ſee and hear from ſome of you, ſcornful cenſuring and condemning others, greedy panting and graſping at the riches, honours, and preferments of this world, fraudulent circumventing and overreaching others, cruel revenges upon thoſe you judge your enemies, bitter quarrelling and contending one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding thoſe miſcarriages, which might juſtly cauſe you with us to lye in the duſt, joyntly bewailing our dreadful tranſgreſſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet wee finde you lifted up, boaſting of the glorious Times, proudly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriating to your ſelves the honourable names of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Saints, the godly party, not remembring the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of our Saviour in the caſe of the Phariſce and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican,<note place="margin">Luk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18. 13</note> or what hee ſometimes ſaid to men, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion was as high as yours, when hee ſaw them lofty:<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 21. 31.</note> Publicans and Harlots ſhall go before you into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
            <p>That you ſeem to us to meaſure the Saintſhip of your ſelves or others, rather by ſome private opinions, or ſome ſmall punctilioes of worſhip, then by the great things of Faith, righteouſneſſe, and mercy, becauſe we find ſome men whoſe profeſſion of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is attended with righteouſneſſe and mercy, yet accounts us no better than
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115496:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
civil by diverſe of you, whilſt others are cried up for Saints and godly, who are much deficient in theſe.</p>
            <p>That you animate and incourage, yea in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure neceſſitate and inforce our Miniſters, to their more harſh and uncharitable dealing with us, it is uſually from you rather than themſelves, that our children are not baptized, nor our ſelves admitted to the other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whilſt they are loath to looſe or anger you and if any of them hath more courage in the caſe of Chriſt; or more bowels of compaſſion towards us, you preſently brand and aſperſe them with your tongues, yea often make ſchiſmes and ſeparations from them.</p>
            <p>That you carry all things towards us in a lofty magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall way, not as Schollers of the higher form (which wee could willinging admit) but as Lords and Maſters over us; though you live in vicinity to us, we ſeldome hear any words of wholeſom counſel or inſtruction from you, unleſſe you get into our Pulpits; neither can we enjoy any communion with you in our Churches, unleſſe all the power may be in your hands, to admit, exclude, rule and order all things at your pleaſure, having forgotten (as wee think) that ſeaſonable counſel of St. <hi>James, My Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>be not many Maſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe powers and priviledges which you challenge as belonging to the Church of Chriſt, you ſhare in a manner wholly to your ſelves, not affording to us any portion in them, you ſay it is in the peoples power to chuſe or reject their Miniſters, yet make no ſcruple to obtrude them upon us, you ſay a Chriſtian ought not to bee rejected or dealt with as an heathen, till hee bee found contumacious after ſeveral admonitions, yet obſerve no ſuch rules in order unto us, as if your very opinion of your ſelves were ſufficient to make you the onely Chriſtians and to intitle you to all the honours or liberties by Chriſt conferred, and your ill opinion of us were ſufficient to degrade us, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude us from the meaneſt priviledge belonging to the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That you indeavour to bring upon us and our poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the ſaddeſt judgement that can befal a nation, namely
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115496:16"/>
to unchurch and unchriſtian us, and as you for the preſent ſeem to account us as Heathens or little better, ſo your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice tendeth (if infinite mercy prevent not) to make us ſuch indeed, whilſt you indeavour, to take from us, and our poſterity, all the marks and badges of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion, and ſo what lyeth in you, wholly to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheire us from the Camp of Chriſt, as if you grudged to ſee the promiſes made by the Father unto Chriſt, of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Nations to bee gathered to him, performed in this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Corner of the world.</p>
            <p>Conſider (wee beſeech you) the infinite mercyes and long-ſuffering of that God whom you profeſs, how excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding flow and loath hee is to caſt off thoſe which are once entred into Covenant with him; what heart breaking ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions hee hath concerning <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> in the height of their apoſtacy and rebellion, and how exceeding<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11. 8 Jer. 3. 15</note> backward he was to give a bill of divorce to either of them, and think how acceptable your indeavours are to Chriſt, who make it ſo ſmall a matter to caſhiere ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, yea, whole Nations from his campe.</p>
            <p>Compare, (wee intreat you) this your way with the preſidents and examples recorded in holy Scripture, and ſee whether the precious ſervants of God there mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, did ever tread this your way of Separation; did <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> or <hi>Samuel?</hi> did <hi>Jeremiah, Ezra,</hi> or <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah?</hi> did our bleſſed Saviour or his Apoſtles, ever ſteer your courſe in order to the corruptions of the Church in their times? did not they lay out their indeavours for the emendation of the whole body? and did not they live in communion with the Church in their times, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways corrupted? Yea look upon the Chriſtian Churches recorded in the new Teſtament, did St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtle, commend to the ſounder part of the Churches of <hi>Corinth</hi> or <hi>Galatia,</hi> any ſuch ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as you indeavour? yea, what ſervants of God did you ever read of in holy Scripture, that did withdraw or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves from the body of the people, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the ſame God with them, upon ſuch pretences as you? or what example do you finde in all the holy Scriptures, that lookes ſo like your caſe, as that of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115496:16"/>
Phariſees, ſo branded by our Saviour.</p>
            <p>Conſider of the ſingular talents that God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon you, and the ſtrickt account that you muſt give concerning your improvement of them, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly bethink your ſelves, whether you might not give a better account continuing in communion with us, and applying your ſelves ſtrongly to our emendation, helping us by your godly counſel and example, and cheerfully aſſiſting us in removing deſperate contemners of God, and all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from communion, than leaving the ſtations where divine providence had ſet you, to cloyſter up your ſelves in ſeparate Congregations, and ſo deprive us your poor brethren, of thoſe helps and aſſiſtances which wee might juſtly have expected from your more eminent abilities.</p>
            <p>Ranſack (we beſeech you) your hearts throughly, to finde out the true root and bottome of this ſpirit of ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and obſerve narrowly whether under other ſpecious pretences, or with ſome pious intentions, there be not a bitter root of pride and haughtineſs, cauſing you to affect ſingularity, and deſire to appear alone to the view of men, thinking it below your worth to be found in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thoſe whom in opinion you have layed ſo much below your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Yea think ſadly whether thoſe manifold revolts that have been made from your ſeparate Congregations, to monſtrous opinions, and unclean converſations, have not been the righteous judgement of God upon you, for your too high valuations of your ſelves, and uncharitable ſeparations from others; whereby you have deprived ſuch poor creatures as we, of thoſe brotherly helps, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, which by your eminent endowments. God had inabled you to yeeld, and by his providence put op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities into your hands to afford unto us.</p>
            <p>What conſtruction you make of theſe paſſages of providence, we know not, but truly to us the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, they appear, ſtrange, and formidable, that whereas you fiſh with ſo great a maſh, that ſcarce one of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred are by you taken and admitted into your Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, that out of this hundreth part of yours, more
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115496:17"/>
ſhould be found revolting to deſperate opinions, than of the ninety nine parts by you deſerted, appeareth to us ſtrange and wonderful, and ſuch as we think may ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally put you upon a juſt ſuſpition, and ſerious re-exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of that way, from which there is ſo eaſie a tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to many dreadful deluſions, and through which ſo many have already paſſed into the campe of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
            <p>Having thus directed our complaints to each of you in particular, we now return unto you all to whom this our mournful ſupplication is intended, and again proſtrate our ſelves before you, humbly beſeeching you, by all the tender compaſſions of that God, who ſtiles himſelf, <hi>The God of mercy, by all the precious blood of Chriſt ſhed for ſuch poor ſinners, by all the bowels of mercy in that Spirit, who</hi> (as we hope) <hi>ruleth in your hearts, by all the bands both natural and civil, wherein we ſtand related unto you, by the invaluable price of an immortal ſoul, and high concernment of an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have pity on us in our ignorance and weakneſs, and apply your ſelves more earneſtly to reſcue us from the rage and malice of our ſoul-devouring enemies; let your endeavours for our help be ſomewhat anſwerable to the greatneſs, of our danger, to the weight of an eternal ſtate, and to the invaluable price paid by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for our redemption.</p>
            <p>What if you finde us peeviſh, froward, and ſometimes ſleighting your Chriſtian endeavours for our good, do not preſently give over, but remember that the great God of heaven hath waited long both upon us and you, be aſſured that we ſhall in the end be convinced of your faithfulneſs, and that what ever thanks you have from us, the Lord Jeſus will certainly remember this work and ſervice of your love.</p>
            <p>O diſſolve not that nail that yet we have in Chriſts holy place! reſtore unto us thoſe colours, which you have begun to take from us, let us be entertained as Schollers though of the loweſt form, as Souldiers, though in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115496:17"/>
meaneſt imployment in the Camp of Chriſt, at leaſt deny us not the favour vouchſaſed to the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> to be as hewers of wood, or drawers of water for the houſe of our God.</p>
            <p>You tell us you have reſcued us from imminent danger of Popery and ſuperſtition, but what comfort will this bee unto us, if you now leave us, and our poſterity to periſh in the deeper gulf of prophaneneſs and heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm?</p>
            <p>Conſider what ſingular advantages you now have upon us for our good, whilſt we maintain the principles of Chriſtianity, and wear the colours of the Lord-Jeſus Chriſt, your principal work is now but to bring us to live up to the principles we do beleeve, and to ſerve that Maſter, whoſe livery we wear.</p>
            <p>But if you leave us till thoſe principles be obliterate, and theſe colours thrown aſide, think ſeriouſly how much more hard, and hopeleſs our condition then will be, eſpecially conſidering that you are not furniſhed with the power of miracles or extraordinary gifts, which have been Gods ordinary means for converting heathens unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O then delay not the time! but haſten with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible diligence unto our reſcue, before the Devil circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent you, and take advantage of your leaving us unto our ſelves, as ſtaving us off from the Ordinances of Chriſt, to harden our hearts, and draw us by degrees to contempt of thoſe things which now we weakly prize, and both you, and we eternally bewail the loſs of theſe preſent opportunities.</p>
            <p>We are yet willing to ingage our children to the Lord in the Sacrament of Baptiſm, we are yet willing to renue our own ingagements unto Chriſt in that other Sacrament, if you would not diſhearten, and diſcourage us, but we finde ſin is of an hardning nature, and that long neglect of duty will diſſolve the ſenſe of obligation, and we cannot but fear, that if we be now neglected by you, it may come to paſs that our hearts may bee ſo hardned, that if God ſhould afterward raiſe up ſome
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115496:18"/>
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> who ſhould call, and invite us, or ours, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our ſelves unto the Lord in theſe ſacred Ordinances, either we or ours ſhould anſwer ſuch gracious invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions after the ſame manner as the moſt of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did the ſummons of that holy King, with ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30. 20</note>
            </p>
            <p>O let this our imminent danger be weighed in your moſt adviſed thoughts, you ſee how many have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready turned their backs on Chriſt, and all his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and are wholly gone after Satan, and how induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous they are to draw others after them, and then think what dangerous temptations you put us the weaker ſort upon, to revolt unto the enemy, whilſt you refuſe to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain us in the Camp of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Minde ſeriouſly (we beſeech you) that great account that you muſt give to your, and our Maſter the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of your faithfulneſs in all your adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in order to the ſouls of men, and conſider what anſwer you will make to him if you ſleight, or neglect ſo great a part of the purchaſe of his blood, or what excuſe you will finde when he ſhall ariſe to plead with you.</p>
            <p>Did not I come from heaven, and give my deareſt life for the redemption of theſe poor ſouls? Did not I with great endeavours, even with the expence of the blood of many my holy Martyrs, bring them under ſolemn bonds and ingagements to my ſelf?</p>
            <p>And when I ſaw them neglected by their former guides, did not I by wondrous providences reſcue them, and deliver them over into your hands that you ſhould feed and teach them?</p>
            <p>And is this your faithfulneſs to me and mine, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the precious food that I provided for them, to leave them to wander in the wilderneſs as ſheep without a Shepherd? yea, to let looſe many ravenous Wolves upon them to devour them, and for an excuſe of this your ſloathfulneſs and treachery, to deface my marks and badges which you found upon them, that ſo you might plead they were none of mine?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115496:18"/>Seemeth it a ſmall thing to you, <hi>O Rams and Hee-goats,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 34 21.</note> 
               <hi>you fatteſt of the flock, that you have taken the beſt of the paſture for your ſelves, but that you have thruſt with the ſhoulder, and the ſide, and puſht with the horns, the weak and diſeaſed of my flock, till you have ſcattered them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O conſider what anſwer you will make to the Lord Jeſus, when he ſhall ariſe and plead with you on our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and how ſad your caſe will be, if the blood of ſo many thouſand ſouls, periſhing through your neglect and careleſneſs, ſhall plead againſt you in the day of wrath.</p>
            <p>We have indeed deſerved from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by our unfruitfulneſs, and many other ſad miſcarriages to be by him totally rejected, and that his Goſpel-ſight ſhould be wholly taken from us; But what have we done to you, that you ſhould deal ſo hardly with us, that you ſhould be the inſtruments to bring this dreadful night of darkneſs on us? Or that you ſhould not rather endeavour our emendation and ſalvation?</p>
            <p>What evil have you obſerved in us, from which your joynt endeavours might not hope to reſcue us? Are wee blinde and ignorant? Yet ſurely not ſo uncapable of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but that your joynt endeavours might even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the moſt ignorant of us to learn the fundamentals of Religion, and ſo much as being practiſed would ſave our ſouls. Are we wrapt and intangled in ſinful luſts? Surely your earneſt and joynt endeavours, might by the bleſſing of the Lord break theſe cords of ſin, and bring us by an holy violence to the obedience of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, we cannot but think that noble King <hi>Joſiah</hi> had as ignorant and ſtubborn a people to deal withall as you, and yet he not alone ingaged them to the Lord in that his ſolemn Paſſeover, but made them ſerve the Lord all<note place="margin">2 Chron 34. 33</note> his dayes.</p>
            <p>We know the donation of life ſupernatural lieth not in your power, but it lieth in your power, to acquaint us with the waies of life, to cauſe us to attend upon the means of grace, to reſtrain us from the outward acts of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115496:19"/>
ſin, yea to ſet and keep us in ſuch waies of worſhip and obedience unto Chriſt, as that you might comfortably hope by Gods bleſſing on your Chriſtian endeavours, to behold us as the Crown of your labour at the great day.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, we beſeech you in your ſerious thoughts, whether a general reformation of the body of the people of this Nation, a re-ingaging them in Covenant, and keeping them at the leaſt in an external obedience unto Chriſt, will not be more for the honour of him to whom the Nations are promiſed for an inheritance, more agrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to your own former Vowes and Covenants, and a more likely way to make you a bleſſing to the people, and them to you, than to leave the main bulk of the people to be overgrown with thorns and briars, to degenerate into an howling wilderneſs, whilſt all your care is laid out upon the culture of ſome few ſmall incloſures.</p>
            <p>What comfort can it be to you, O Magiſtrates! to have the bonds between Chriſt Jeſus, and this Nation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued through the revolutions of ſo many hundred years diſſolved in your dayes?</p>
            <p>Or to you, O Miniſters! to have the foundations of Religion, which you found laid in the hearts of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the people of this Nation, quite demoliſhed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your adminiſtrations?</p>
            <p>Or to you that call your ſelves the godly party, to have the Chriſtian Religion, which formerly did over-ſpread the whole ſurface of this Nation, now abridged to your few ſeparate Congregations?</p>
            <p>Or what heart, that is not altogether ſtupid, can behold the great endeavours, and high profeſſions for Religion found in the beginning of theſe times, and in a ſad revolt of ſo great a part of the Nation back again to heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, or the like abominations, and not bewail it with a flood of tears?</p>
            <p>We have thus ſpread our mournful caſe before you, hoping that, the God of all grace and mercy, in whoſe hand are the hearts and wayes of all the ſons of men, will incline your hearts to pity our ſad condition, and more
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115496:19"/>
compaſſionately to apply your ſelves unto our help, for which purpoſe we now make our humble addreſſes unto him, who gave his pretious blood a ranſome for us.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Glorious Prince, and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and merciful high Prieſt of our Profeſſion, who didſt for our ſakes ſuffer, and wert tempted, that thou mighteſt be touched with the feeling of our infirmities, and know ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally to pity us in our temptations, have mercy upon us, have mercy upon us, O bleſſed Saviour, and grant that theſe our mournful complaints and ſupplications, may pierce the ears and hearts of thy Vicegerents, and Ambaſſadors, with all the more eminent of thy pretious ſervants amongſt us, that our eternal welfare may be more cordially regarded by them, that they may more faithfully and diligently lay out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and al their abilities for the ſalvation of thoſe ſouls whom thou haſt bought with thy pretious blood, Let our Magiſtrates inherit the zeal of <hi>Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> and other famous nurſing Fathers of thy Church of old; Let our Miniſters, as thy dear Apoſtle <hi>Paul, be willing to ſpend and be ſpent for our ſalvation;</hi> Let the impreſſions of thy tender mercies be upon all the more knowing of thy ſervants, that they may compaſſionately imploy all their abilities for our emendation and ſalvation. O thou that wept over thy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when they would not own thee; Let us, who (<hi>though unworthy</hi>) are called by thy Name, and have taken hold of thy Covenant, taſte of thy tender compaſſions. Look down from heaven the habitation of thine holineſs, <hi>Where is thy zeal, and thy ſtrength, and the ſounding of thy bowels towards us; Doubtleſs thou art our Redeemer, though our Fathers be ignorant of us, and our Elders will not own us, thou art our Redeemer, and thy name from everlaſting; O do not ſuffer us to erre from thy wayes, do not harden our hearts from thy fear.</hi> Wee cannot expect the like compaſſions from ſinful man, as from thee, O bleſſed <hi>Immanuel,</hi> who felt the pains of our redemption, not <hi>Paul,</hi> but thou, O Chriſt, wert crucified for us, we cannot repoſe in any other arms but thine, who carrieſt the feeble lambs in the boſome of thy love.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115496:20"/>
Though the Prieſt and Levite paſs by on the other ſide, yet thou the good Samaritan have compaſſion on us, and poure thine oyl and wine into our wounds, and the more we are neglected by men, the more forcible and alluring let the cords of thy love be to us, though the hearts of men melt not over our miſery, yet let thy bowels of compaſſion yern upon us, and let us not loſe our hold of thy Covenant, but ſtill be refreſhed with thy protection, and rejoyce under the ſhadow of all thine Ordinances. Look down from heaven, and behold this Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and the Vine which thy right hand hath planted in this Nation, make up the hedge of thy providence about it, and let not the Boar of the Forreſt continue to waſte it, or the wilde beaſt of the field to devour it. Return, O Lord, and let it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thee concerning thy ſervants, and let not the evil that is already come upon us appear little before thee.</p>
               <p>Heal thou the dreadful breaches and diſtractions which the cruel enemy hath cauſed amongſt us, repair the ruined walls of thy <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Grant the ſpirit of unity and charity to thy people of this Nation, that thy family here may be truly a family of love, and on their doors engraven, <hi>Here is no ſtrife, for we are brethren.</hi> O Lord hear, O Lord forgive, and heal our deſolations, remember not againſt us former iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, let thy tender mercies ſpeedily prevent us, wee are brought very low. Help us, O God of our ſalvation, for the glory of thy name, deliver us, and purge away our ſins for thy names ſake; So we thy people, and ſheep of thy paſture, ſhall give thee thanks for ever, and teach our children to celebrate thy praiſe to all Generations.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
